Welcome back to our next video, mastering the command prompt along the power of Windows
command line C-L-I command line interface command prompt C-M-T okay so in this video we are
going to understand what is C-M-D how to use C-M-D because if you are a network engineer
if you are a administrator of any level, at that in the leader level or in a level engineer
who is just learning, you have to use C-M-D more than 15 times per day if you are actively
working on network operations, there is a lot of things that you can do from the command
prompt that is necessary, that is necessary to understand how our network is working, if
our system is working or not, if this IP address is reachable or not from your system
for your firewall from your switch, so it is very important to find to understand that C-M-D
commands, these commands are just like prompts okay, in ARD present intelligent, we use
English prompt, English language prompt to tell or to get information but here we have
a keyword we have is to be stored keyword, that we use to find out a related information
to us, so we are going to explore essential command prompt to enhance your windows table
sorting, network like knows and system management skills, what is the C-M-D, what is the
command prompt, it is a built-in command line interface, it the empowered user to execute
test-based instruction offering deeper control than the graphical user interface, C-M-D
is invaluable for travel sorting, automatic tasks and accessing system function otherwise
unavailable, what is C-M-D, and why C-M-D, code network commands as well, so why C-M-D,
efficient task of permission, network and system technology, advanced system control, code
network commands, IP config net state, we are going to see this and there is a lot of
things, these are just little bit, we have to understand in very deep manner, what is
IP config, when we write this right now in your system open C-M-D and write IP config, there
is a lot of information you get there, so it will display current network interface,
IP configuration, your current IP does and your subnet ask you get better details, your
MAC does, this is a lot of things, as well as you can change it by using a flash, okay,
the flash is a command, this is very essential for network travel sorting, same net
state, provide information on network connection routing table interface, static, what
are the connections you have established in your system to other side, you can find out
every thing, so whenever there is an attack with a switch with a firewall or with a device
and devices computer laptop, network engineer go and check with a net set that there is
a number of communication is going on with the system and check if anyone is malicious,
then we have to stop that communication right now, so this is that is why it is very important,
so whenever any switch, any end point or any device get infected with the virus, we have
to accelerate, how are you going to oscillating, just power off, just remove the power, let
us move ahead, advanced network timers, what is NBT stack, what is trace ERT, it is trace
root, what is NBT stack, display net verse over TCP IP protocol, statistic helpful for
diagnosing, net verse name resolution issue and checking connection status, so when you are
joining, you first step, you are basic step, is that you have to learn this command for
any tool, so you first know that okay, so this is the issue or this is not an issue,
you have to check with the CMD command prompts, it will trace the path data packet
take to the destination, identify a button next or failure along a network to a specific
IP or ERT, so in a network operation, we get a lot of data like queries like I am not able
to access this particular device, I am not able to access this particular camera, now what
do you have to do, go to the command prompt, write down this prompt, trace root, TRA, CE
RT and then there is a space, then the IP of that camera, now it will tell you that
your system goes to your gateway, okay, now from gateway, it goes to your core switch,
from core switch, it goes to your firewall and if firewall is going to camera or not,
if not, you have to troubles with your firewall, you have to check that if firewall has
that path took the camera or not, now if core one switch is not able to going forward
to firewall, then you have to find out that if there is any ACL in your switch or not,
so this time of thing you have to troubles with using a threshold, now there is a like,
there is a more on, you have to drive your oneself, I can tell everything, I can define
everything that this command do, this command, but when you type on your system, it will
give you a lot of more insights, more your information that you can speak to your interview
or you use it in a real world, when you in a job, so this command of fundamental for network
administrator and IT professional to maintain healthy and efficient network operation and
understanding where output can quickly pick out the source of connectivity problem, let's
going a little bit deep doing, deep dive into connected tools, but this is that's it, we don't
go much deal, what is a path thing, can you see comprehensive network analysis, now when you have
to find out that a pin and please both are working or not, no, don't need to use separate
separate, come on, just go path pin, combine path pin and test load function, provide
data information on the packet loss at each hop network path idle for pin pointing performance
degradation, so let's now just do a ping to 8.8.8.8 or 4.2.2, it will ping to Google, now you
ping, you will get a lot of information that use in 5 packets of this size a 32 bit and you
get a 5 or loss of 5 depend on the connectivity, sometimes you lost but with the Google
you always get up ping, but with the when you have devices which are sometimes reachable
ISP which are sometime up, sometime down, so it's different on that, some things you get,
some ping you get lost, that's how it work, sometime it gives you a two deco stemmed out,
so it's depend on the situation which is currently there and it is for DNS resolution
diagnostics, query the DNS domain name system, so in past videos I told you to find out
the full form of DNS, what is DNS, now here you can see that it's domain name system,
to resolve IP address from domain names or vice versa, crucial for diagnosing DNS related
issue in verifying domain name visual resolution, so there's a lot of time there, what will
happen that a DNS is not resolved, so when DNS is not resolved, domain name system
is not resolved, now you learn, now you just Google how DNS work, how DNS work, so
when the DNS does not get resolved, you get a error page in your browser, you not able
to access any website, because DNS is not resolved, now FTP it's just a file test of protocol,
it enable a file transfer between the computer when it works, there's not much with the
related to the same device, you have to check that, sometime you have to check that, FTP
is working on not a telelet which is used to take remote access of any system, any devices
with this computer desktop, in we will talk about a computer, commonly used for a protocol
or not going to file from the server, particularly for the same management, large data
transfer, here it is, a 10 network, a remote login, like you see, enable remote login
to other computer over network while useful for network diagnosis, it largely says,
press to buy more secure protocol like secure shell due to its unencrypted nature, system
and for it we will give you the detailed information of a system, everything like computer,
RAM, OS or Zinnit have architecture you have, we will give you a lot of information for
troubleshooting the system, if you don't know the system, like you go to your end users,
any user side and you get their data, you get their system to troubleshoot, now you just
pull this prompt on your assembly and you get all the information that you want, now G
update, it's a group policy request, update your group policy setting on the computer,
critical for a middle year playing, it's a policy change without requiring a system to
start, especially in managed network environment, so in this, what will happen in that
when there is a network of a local, a company network, it is a group policy is published
on all over the domains of a system, so sometimes you do not get that group policy, it will affect
your system performance, so now you will need to manually fetch that group policy or refresh
the group policy, so if your system is not able to fetch that policy after refreshing, it will,
so it will start working most of the time, now most of the time, more command
expert that you have to explore, it is task list, let's task a check what we'll do, it
actually do to manage running process, set down, what to do, check, go and do the
write down the command on your command program, disk part, what will will tell you, sfc,
scan and repair, correct system file, it will tell you the more it is, see a sketch disk,
check disk for error, so these are the command that you have to do, check it and this, like,
you have all you can get all more same degree commands for you as well, if you want to,
I will prod also but you, it will be great if you google and then try it on your system,
it, it was just basic overview of CMD, that what it is and how it works and what you can do,
okay, thank you very much, we will meet you in our next video, by the way, this is sufficient
to, correct any interview, okay, bye bye,